<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Apache DataFusion Blog - Andrew Lamb (InfluxData)</title><link href="https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/feeds/andrew-lamb-influxdata.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/</id><updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Using External Indexes, Metadata Stores, Catalogs and Caches to Accelerate Queries on Apache Parquet</title><link href="https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/2025/08/15/external-parquet-indexes" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Andrew Lamb (InfluxData)</name></author><id>tag:datafusion.apache.org,2025-08-15:/blog/2025/08/15/external-parquet-indexes</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--
{% comment %}
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
{% endcomment %}
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a common misconception that &lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Parquet&lt;/a&gt; requires (slow) reparsing of
metadata and is limited to indexing structures provided by the format. In fact,
caching parsed metadata and using custom external indexes along with
Parquet's hierarchical data organization can significantly speed up query
processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I describe …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!--
{% comment %}
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
{% endcomment %}
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a common misconception that &lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Parquet&lt;/a&gt; requires (slow) reparsing of
metadata and is limited to indexing structures provided by the format. In fact,
caching parsed metadata and using custom external indexes along with
Parquet's hierarchical data organization can significantly speed up query
processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I describe the role of external indexes, caches, and metadata
stores in high performance systems, and demonstrate how to apply these concepts
to Parquet processing using &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/"&gt;Apache DataFusion&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Note this is an expanded
version of the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=74YsJT1-Rdk"&gt;companion video&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1e_Z_F8nt2rcvlNvhU11khF5lzJJVqNtqtyJ-G3mp4-Q/edit"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;System designers choose between a pre-configured data system or the often
daunting task of building their own custom data platform from scratch.
For many users and use cases, one of the existing data systems will
likely be good enough. However, traditional systems such as &lt;a href="https://spark.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Spark&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://duckdb.org/"&gt;DuckDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://clickhouse.com/"&gt;ClickHouse&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://hive.apache.org/"&gt;Hive&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://www.snowflake.com/"&gt;Snowflake&lt;/a&gt; are each optimized for a certain set of
tradeoffs between performance, cost, availability, interoperability, deployment
target, cloud / on-premises, operational ease and many other factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For new, or especially demanding use cases, where no existing system makes your
optimal tradeoffs, you can build your own custom data platform. Previously this
was a long and expensive endeavor, but today, in the era of &lt;a href="https://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol16/p2679-pedreira.pdf"&gt;Composable Data
Systems&lt;/a&gt;, it is increasingly feasible. High quality, open source building blocks
such as &lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Parquet&lt;/a&gt; for storage, &lt;a href="https://arrow.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Arrow&lt;/a&gt; for in-memory processing,
and &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/"&gt;Apache DataFusion&lt;/a&gt; for query execution make it possible to quickly build
custom data platforms optimized for your specific
needs&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction to External Indexes / Catalogs / Metadata Stores / Caches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Using External Indexes to Accelerate Queries" class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/external-index-overview.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Using external indexes to speed up queries in an analytic system.
Given a user's query (Step 1), the system uses an external index (one that is not
stored inline in the data files) to quickly find files that may contain
relevant data (Step 2). Then, for each file, the system uses the external index
to further narrow the required data to only those &lt;strong&gt;parts&lt;/strong&gt; of each file
(e.g. data pages) that are relevant (Step 3). Finally, the system reads only those
parts of the file and returns the results to the user (Step 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I use the term &lt;strong&gt;"index"&lt;/strong&gt; to mean any structure that helps
locate relevant data during processing, and a high level overview of how
external indexes are used to speed up queries is shown in Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Data Systems typically store both the data itself and additional information
(metadata) to more quickly find data relevant to a query. Metadata is often
stored in structures with names like "index," "catalog" and "cache" and the
terminology varies widely across systems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many different types of indexes, types of content stored in indexes,
strategies to keep indexes up to date, and ways to apply indexes during query
processing. These differences each have their own set of tradeoffs, and thus
different systems understandably make different choices depending on their use
case. There is no one-size-fits-all solution for indexing. For example, Hive
uses the &lt;a href="https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/Hive/Design#Design-Metastore"&gt;Hive Metastore&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.vertica.com/"&gt;Vertica&lt;/a&gt; uses a purpose-built &lt;a href="https://www.vertica.com/docs/latest/HTML/Content/Authoring/AdministratorsGuide/Managing/Metadata/CatalogOverview.htm"&gt;Catalog&lt;/a&gt; and open
data lake systems typically use a table format like &lt;a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Iceberg&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://delta.io/"&gt;Delta
Lake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Indexes&lt;/strong&gt; store information separately ("external") to the data
itself. External indexes are flexible and widely used, but require additional
operational overhead to keep in sync with the data files. For example, if you
add a new Parquet file to your data lake you must also update the relevant
external index to include information about the new file. Note, it &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt;
possible to avoid external indexes by only using information from the data files
themselves, such as embed user-defined indexes directly in Parquet files,
described in our previous blog &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/2025/07/14/user-defined-parquet-indexes/"&gt;Embedding User-Defined Indexes in Apache Parquet
Files&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of information commonly stored in external indexes include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Min/Max statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloom filters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inverted indexes / Full Text indexes &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information needed to read the remote file (e.g the schema, or Parquet footer metadata)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use case specific indexes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of locations external indexes can be stored include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Separate files&lt;/strong&gt; such as a &lt;a href="https://www.json.org/"&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; or Parquet file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transactional databases&lt;/strong&gt; such as a &lt;a href="https://www.postgresql.org/"&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt; table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed key-value store&lt;/strong&gt; such as &lt;a href="https://redis.io/"&gt;Redis&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://cassandra.apache.org/"&gt;Cassandra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local memory&lt;/strong&gt; such as an in memory hash map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using Apache Parquet for Storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the rest of this blog focuses on building custom external indexes using
Parquet and DataFusion, I first briefly discuss why Parquet is a good choice
for modern analytic systems. The research community frequently confuses
limitations of a particular &lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/docs/file-format/implementationstatus/"&gt;implementation of the Parquet format&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/documentation/latest/"&gt;Parquet Format&lt;/a&gt; itself and it is important to clarify this distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apache Parquet's combination of good compression, high-performance, high quality
open source libraries, and wide ecosystem interoperability make it a compelling
choice when building new systems. While there are some niche use cases that may
benefit from specialized formats, Parquet is typically the obvious choice.
While recent proprietary file formats differ in details, they all use the same
high level structure&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metadata (typically at the end  of the file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data divided into columns and then into horizontal slices (e.g. Parquet Row Groups and/or Data Pages). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure is so widespread because it enables the hierarchical pruning
approach described in the next section. For example, the native &lt;a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/engines/table-engines/mergetree-family/mergetree"&gt;Clickhouse
MergeTree&lt;/a&gt; format consists of &lt;em&gt;Parts&lt;/em&gt; (similar to Parquet files), and &lt;em&gt;Granules&lt;/em&gt;
(similar to Row Groups). The &lt;a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/guides/best-practices/sparse-primary-indexes#clickhouse-index-design"&gt;Clickhouse indexing strategy&lt;/a&gt; follows a classic
hierarchical pruning approach that first locates the Parts and then the Granules
that may contain relevant data for the query. This is exactly the same pattern
as Parquet based systems, which first locate the relevant Parquet files and then
the Row Groups / Data Pages within those files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common criticism of using Parquet is that it is not as performant as some new
proposal. These criticisms typically cherry-pick a few queries and/or datasets
and build a specialized index or data layout for that specific cases. However,
as I explain in the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=74YsJT1-Rdk"&gt;companion video&lt;/a&gt; of this blog, even for
&lt;a href="https://clickbench.com/"&gt;ClickBench&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the current
benchmaxxing&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; target of analytics vendors, there is
less than a factor of two difference in performance between custom file formats
and Parquet. The difference becomes even lower when using Parquet files that
actually use the full range of existing Parquet features such Column and Offset
Indexes and Bloom Filters&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Compared to the low
interoperability and expensive transcoding/loading step of alternate file
formats, Parquet is hard to beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hierarchical Pruning Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key technique for optimizing query processing systems is quickly skipping as
much data as quickly as possible. Analytic systems typically use a hierarchical
approach to progressively narrow the set of data that needs to be processed. 
The standard approach is shown in Figure 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entire files are ruled out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within each file, large sections (e.g. Row Groups) are ruled out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Optionally) smaller sections (e.g. Data Pages) are ruled out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, the system reads only the relevant data pages and applies the query
   predicate to the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Standard Pruning Layers." class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/processing-pipeline.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Hierarchical Pruning: The system first rules out files, then
Row Groups, then Data Pages, and finally reads only the relevant data pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process is hierarchical because the per-row computation required at the
earlier stages (e.g. skipping a entire file) is lower than the computation
required at later stages (apply predicates to the data). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, while the details of what metadata is used and how that
metadata is managed varies substantially across query systems, they almost all
use a hierarchical pruning strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apache Parquet Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section provides a brief background on the organization of Apache Parquet
files which is needed to fully understand the sections on implementing external indexes.
If you are already familiar with Parquet, you can skip this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logically, Parquet files are organized into  &lt;em&gt;Row Groups&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Column Chunks&lt;/em&gt; as
shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Logical Parquet File layout: Row Groups and Column Chunks." class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/parquet-layout.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Logical Parquet File Layout: Data is first divided in horizontal slices
called Row Groups. The data is then stored column by column in &lt;em&gt;Column Chunks&lt;/em&gt;.
This arrangement allows efficient access to only the portions of columns needed
for a query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physically, Parquet data is stored as a series of Data Pages along with metadata
stored at the end of the file (in the footer), as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Physical Parquet File layout: Metadata and Footer." class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/parquet-metadata.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;: Physical Parquet File Layout: A typical Parquet file is composed
of many data pages,  which contain the raw encoded data, and a footer that
stores metadata about the file, including the schema and the location of the
relevant data pages, and optional statistics such as min/max values for each
Column Chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parquet files are organized to minimize IO and processing using two key mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Projection Pushdown&lt;/strong&gt;: if a query needs only a subset of columns from a table, it
   only needs to read the pages for the relevant Column Chunks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filter Pushdown&lt;/strong&gt;: Similarly, given a query with a filter predicate such as
   &lt;code&gt;WHERE C &amp;gt; 25&lt;/code&gt;, query engines can use statistics such as (but not limited to)
   the min/max values stored in the metadata to skip reading and decoding pages that
   cannot possibly match the predicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high level mechanics of Parquet predicate pushdown is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Parquet Filter Pushdown: use filter predicate to skip pages." class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/parquet-filter-pushdown.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;: Filter Pushdown in Parquet: query engines use the the predicate,
&lt;code&gt;C &amp;gt; 25&lt;/code&gt;, from the query along with statistics from the metadata, to identify
pages that may match the predicate which are read for further processing. 
Please refer to the &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/blog/2025/03/21/parquet-pushdown"&gt;Efficient Filter Pushdown&lt;/a&gt; blog for more details.
&lt;strong&gt;NOTE the exact same pattern can be applied using information from external
indexes, as described in the next sections.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pruning Files with External Indexes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in hierarchical pruning is quickly ruling out files that cannot
match the query.  For example, if a system expects to have see queries that
apply to a time range, it might create an external index to store the minimum
and maximum &lt;code&gt;time&lt;/code&gt; values for each file. Then, during query processing, the
system can quickly rule out files that can not possible contain relevant data.
For example, if the user issues a query that only matches the last 7 days of
data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-sql"&gt;WHERE time &amp;gt; now() - interval '7 days'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The index can quickly rule out files that only have data older than 7 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TODO update the diagram to match the example above -- and have time predicates --&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Data Skipping: Pruning Files." class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/prune-files.png" width="80%"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt;: Step 1: File Pruning. Given a query predicate, systems use external
indexes to quickly rule out files that cannot match the query. In this case, by
consulting the index all but two files can be ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many different systems that use external indexes to find files such as 
&lt;a href="https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/Hive/Design#Design-Metastore"&gt;Hive Metadata Store&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/"&gt;Iceberg&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href="https://delta.io/"&gt;Delta Lake&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://duckdb.org/2025/05/27/ducklake.html"&gt;DuckLake&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="https://sparkbyexamples.com/apache-hive/hive-partitions-explained-with-examples/"&gt;Hive Style Partitioning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
Of course, each of these systems works well for their intended usecases, but
if none meets your needs, or you want to experiment with
different strategies, you can easily build your own external index using
DataFusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pruning Files with External Indexes Using DataFusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To implement file pruning in DataFusion, you implement a custom &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/trait.TableProvider.html"&gt;TableProvider&lt;/a&gt;
with the &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/trait.TableProvider.html#method.supports_filters_pushdown"&gt;supports_filter_pushdown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/trait.TableProvider.html#tymethod.scan"&gt;scan&lt;/a&gt; methods. The
&lt;code&gt;supports_filter_pushdown&lt;/code&gt; method tells DataFusion which predicates can be used
by the &lt;code&gt;TableProvider&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;scan&lt;/code&gt; method uses those predicates with the
external index to find the files that may contain data that matches the query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DataFusion repository contains a fully working and well-commented example,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion/blob/main/datafusion-examples/examples/parquet_index.rs"&gt;parquet_index.rs&lt;/a&gt;, of this technique that you can use as a starting point. 
The example creates a simple index that stores the min/max values for a column
called &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; along with the file name. Then it runs the following query:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-sql"&gt;SELECT file_name, value FROM index_table WHERE value = 150
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The custom &lt;code&gt;IndexTableProvider&lt;/code&gt;'s &lt;code&gt;scan&lt;/code&gt; method uses the index to find files
that may contain data matching the predicate as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-rust"&gt;impl TableProvider for IndexTableProvider {
    async fn scan(
        &amp;amp;self,
        state: &amp;amp;dyn Session,
        projection: Option&amp;lt;&amp;amp;Vec&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;&amp;gt;,
        filters: &amp;amp;[Expr],
        limit: Option&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;,
    ) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;Arc&amp;lt;dyn ExecutionPlan&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
        let df_schema = DFSchema::try_from(self.schema())?;
        // Combine all the filters into a single ANDed predicate
        let predicate = conjunction(filters.to_vec());

        // Use the index to find the files that might have data that matches the
        // predicate. Any file that can not have data that matches the predicate
        // will not be returned.
        let files = self.index.get_files(predicate.clone())?;

        let object_store_url = ObjectStoreUrl::parse("file://")?;
        let source = Arc::new(ParquetSource::default().with_predicate(predicate));
        let mut file_scan_config_builder =
            FileScanConfigBuilder::new(object_store_url, self.schema(), source)
                .with_projection(projection.cloned())
                .with_limit(limit);

        // Add the files to the scan config
        for file in files {
            file_scan_config_builder = file_scan_config_builder.with_file(
                PartitionedFile::new(file.path(), file_size.size()),
            );
        }
        Ok(DataSourceExec::from_data_source(
            file_scan_config_builder.build(),
        ))
    }
    ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DataFusion handles the details of pushing down the filters to the
&lt;code&gt;TableProvider&lt;/code&gt; and the mechanics of reading the parquet files, so you can focus
on the system specific details such as building, storing and applying the index.
While this example uses a standard min/max index, you can implement any indexing
strategy you need, such as a bloom filters, a full text index, or a more complex
multi-dimensional index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DataFusion also includes several libraries to help with common filtering and
pruning tasks, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full and well documented expression representation (&lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/logical_expr/enum.Expr.html"&gt;Expr&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/logical_expr/enum.Expr.html#visiting-and-rewriting-exprs"&gt;APIs for
  building, visiting, and rewriting&lt;/a&gt; query predicates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Range Based Pruning (&lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/physical_optimizer/pruning/struct.PruningPredicate.html"&gt;PruningPredicate&lt;/a&gt;) for cases where your index stores min/max values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expression simplification (&lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/optimizer/simplify_expressions/struct.ExprSimplifier.html#method.simplify"&gt;ExprSimplifier&lt;/a&gt;) for simplifying predicates before applying them to the index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Range analysis for predicates (&lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/physical_expr/intervals/cp_solver/index.html"&gt;cp_solver&lt;/a&gt;) for interval-based range analysis (e.g. &lt;code&gt;col &amp;gt; 5 AND col &amp;lt; 10&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pruning Parts of Parquet Files with External Indexes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the set of files to be scanned has been determined, the next step in the
hierarchical pruning process is to further narrow down the data within each file.
Similarly to the previous step, almost all advanced query processing systems use additional
metadata to prune unnecessary parts of the file, such as &lt;a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/optimize/skipping-indexes"&gt;Data Skipping Indexes
in ClickHouse&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Parquet-based systems, the most common strategy is using the built-in metadata such
as &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/parquet-format/blob/1dbc814b97c9307687a2e4bee55545ab6a2ef106/src/main/thrift/parquet.thrift#L267"&gt;min/max statistics&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://parquet.apache.org/docs/file-format/bloomfilter/"&gt;Bloom Filters&lt;/a&gt;). However, it is also possible to use external
indexes for filtering &lt;em&gt;WITHIN&lt;/em&gt; Parquet files as shown below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Data Skipping: Pruning Row Groups and DataPages" class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/external-parquet-indexes/prune-row-groups.png" width="80%"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt;: Step 2: Pruning Parquet Row Groups and Data Pages. Given a query predicate,
systems can use external indexes / metadata stores as well as Parquet's built-in
structures to quickly rule out Row Groups and Data Pages that cannot match the query.
In this case, the index has ruled out all but three data pages which must then be fetched
for more processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pruning Parts of Parquet Files with External Indexes using DataFusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To implement pruning within Parquet files, you use the same [&lt;code&gt;TableProvider&lt;/code&gt;] APIs
as for pruning files. For each file your provider wants to scan, you provide 
an additional &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/physical_plan/parquet/struct.ParquetAccessPlan.html"&gt;ParquetAccessPlan&lt;/a&gt; that tells DataFusion what parts of the file to read. This plan is
then &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/physical_plan/parquet/source/struct.ParquetSource.html#implementing-external-indexes"&gt;further refined by the DataFusion Parquet reader&lt;/a&gt; using the built-in
Parquet metadata to potentially prune additional row groups and data pages
during query execution. You can find a full working example in
the &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion/blob/main/datafusion-examples/examples/advanced_parquet_index.rs"&gt;advanced_parquet_index.rs&lt;/a&gt; example of the DataFusion repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how you build a &lt;code&gt;ParquetAccessPlan&lt;/code&gt; to scan only specific row groups
and rows within those row groups. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-rust"&gt;// Default to scan all (4) row groups
let mut access_plan = ParquetAccessPlan::new_all(4);
access_plan.skip(0); // skip row group 0
// Specify scanning rows 100-200 and 350-400
// in row group 1 that has 1000 rows
let row_selection = RowSelection::from(vec![
   RowSelector::skip(100),
   RowSelector::select(100),
   RowSelector::skip(150),
   RowSelector::select(50),
   RowSelector::skip(600),  // skip last 600 rows
]);
access_plan.scan_selection(1, row_selection);
access_plan.skip(2); // skip row group 2
// all of row group 3 is scanned by default
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rows that are selected by the resulting plan look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-text"&gt;&amp;boxdr; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxdl;

&amp;boxv;                   &amp;boxv;  SKIP

&amp;boxur; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxul;
Row Group 0
&amp;boxdr; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxdl;
 &amp;boxdr;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxdl;    SCAN ONLY ROWS
&amp;boxv;&amp;boxur;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxul; &amp;boxv;  100-200
 &amp;boxdr;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxdl;    350-400
&amp;boxv;&amp;boxur;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxul; &amp;boxv;
&amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh;
Row Group 1
&amp;boxdr; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxdl;
       SKIP
&amp;boxv;                   &amp;boxv;

&amp;boxur; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxh; &amp;boxul;
Row Group 2
&amp;boxdr;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxdl;
&amp;boxv;                   &amp;boxv;  SCAN ALL ROWS
&amp;boxv;                   &amp;boxv;
&amp;boxv;                   &amp;boxv;
&amp;boxur;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxh;&amp;boxul;
Row Group 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;code&gt;scan&lt;/code&gt; method, you return an &lt;code&gt;ExecutionPlan&lt;/code&gt; that includes the
&lt;code&gt;ParquetAccessPlan&lt;/code&gt; for each file as shows below (again, slightly simplified for
clarity):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-rust"&gt;impl TableProvider for IndexTableProvider {
    async fn scan(
        &amp;amp;self,
        state: &amp;amp;dyn Session,
        projection: Option&amp;lt;&amp;amp;Vec&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;&amp;gt;,
        filters: &amp;amp;[Expr],
        limit: Option&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;,
    ) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;Arc&amp;lt;dyn ExecutionPlan&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
        let indexed_file = &amp;amp;self.indexed_file;
        let predicate = self.filters_to_predicate(state, filters)?;

        // Use the external index to create a starting ParquetAccessPlan
        // that determines which row groups to scan based on the predicate
        let access_plan = self.create_plan(&amp;amp;predicate)?;

        let partitioned_file = indexed_file
            .partitioned_file()
            // provide the access plan to the DataSourceExec by
            // storing it as  "extensions" on PartitionedFile
            .with_extensions(Arc::new(access_plan) as _);

        let file_source = Arc::new(
            ParquetSource::default()
                // provide the predicate to the standard DataFusion source as well so
                // DataFusion's parquet reader will apply row group pruning based on
                // the built-in parquet metadata (min/max, bloom filters, etc) as well
                .with_predicate(predicate)
        );
        let file_scan_config =
            FileScanConfigBuilder::new(object_store_url, schema, file_source)
                .with_limit(limit)
                .with_projection(projection.cloned())
                .with_file(partitioned_file)
                .build();

        // Finally, put it all together into a DataSourceExec
        Ok(DataSourceExec::from_data_source(file_scan_config))
    }
    ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caching Parquet Metadata&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often said that Parquet is unsuitable for low latency query systems
because the footer must be read and parsed for each query. This is simply not
true, and &lt;strong&gt;many systems use Parquet for low latency analytics and cache the parsed
metadata in memory to avoid re-reading and re-parsing the footer for each query&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Caching Parquet Metadata using DataFusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reusing cached Parquet Metadata is also shown in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion/blob/main/datafusion-examples/examples/advanced_parquet_index.rs"&gt;advanced_parquet_index.rs&lt;/a&gt;
example. The example reads and caches the metadata for each file when the index
is first built and then uses the cached metadata when reading the files during
query execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that thanks to &lt;a href="https://nuno-faria.github.io/"&gt;Nuno Faria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/jonathanc-n"&gt;Jonathan Chen&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/shehabgamin"&gt;Shehab Amin&lt;/a&gt; the built
in &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/listing/struct.ListingTable.html"&gt;ListingTable&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code&gt;TableProvider&lt;/code&gt; included with DataFusion will cache Parquet
metadata in the next release of DataFusion (50.0.0). See the &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion/issues/17000"&gt;mini epic&lt;/a&gt; for
details).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid reparsing the metadata, first implement a custom
&lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/physical_plan/trait.ParquetFileReaderFactory.html"&gt;ParquetFileReaderFactory&lt;/a&gt; as shown below, again slightly simplified for
clarity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-rust"&gt;impl ParquetFileReaderFactory for CachedParquetFileReaderFactory {
    fn create_reader(
        &amp;amp;self,
        _partition_index: usize,
        file_meta: FileMeta,
        metadata_size_hint: Option&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;,
        _metrics: &amp;amp;ExecutionPlanMetricsSet,
    ) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;Box&amp;lt;dyn AsyncFileReader + Send&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
        let filename = file_meta.location();

        // Pass along the information to access the underlying storage
        // (e.g. S3, GCS, local filesystem, etc)
        let object_store = Arc::clone(&amp;amp;self.object_store);
        let mut inner =
            ParquetObjectReader::new(object_store, file_meta.object_meta.location)
                .with_file_size(file_meta.object_meta.size);

        // retrieve the pre-parsed metadata from the cache
        // (which was built when the index was built and is kept in memory)
        let metadata = self
            .metadata
            .get(&amp;amp;filename)
            .expect("metadata for file not found: {filename}");

        // Return a ParquetReader that uses the cached metadata
        Ok(Box::new(ParquetReaderWithCache {
            filename,
            metadata: Arc::clone(metadata),
            inner,
        }))
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in your &lt;a href="https://docs.rs/datafusion/latest/datafusion/datasource/trait.TableProvider.html"&gt;TableProvider&lt;/a&gt; use the factory to avoid re-reading the metadata
for each file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-rust"&gt;impl TableProvider for IndexTableProvider {
    async fn scan(
        &amp;amp;self,
        state: &amp;amp;dyn Session,
        projection: Option&amp;lt;&amp;amp;Vec&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;&amp;gt;,
        filters: &amp;amp;[Expr],
        limit: Option&amp;lt;usize&amp;gt;,
    ) -&amp;gt; Result&amp;lt;Arc&amp;lt;dyn ExecutionPlan&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
        // Configure a factory interface to avoid re-reading the metadata for each file
        let reader_factory =
            CachedParquetFileReaderFactory::new(Arc::clone(&amp;amp;self.object_store))
                .with_file(indexed_file);

        // build the partitioned file (see example above for details)
        let partitioned_file = ...; 

        // Create the ParquetSource with the predicate and the factory
        let file_source = Arc::new(
            ParquetSource::default()
                // provide the factory to create parquet reader without re-reading metadata
                .with_parquet_file_reader_factory(Arc::new(reader_factory)),
        );

        // Pass along the information needed to read the files
        let file_scan_config =
            FileScanConfigBuilder::new(object_store_url, schema, file_source)
                .with_limit(limit)
                .with_projection(projection.cloned())
                .with_file(partitioned_file)
                .build();

        // Finally, put it all together into a DataSourceExec
        Ok(DataSourceExec::from_data_source(file_scan_config))
    }
    ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parquet has the right structure for high performance analytics via hierarchical
pruning, and it is straightforward to build external indexes to speed up queries
using DataFusion without changing the file format. If you need to build a custom
data platform, it has never been easier to build it with Parquet and DataFusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a firm believer that data systems of the future will be built on a
foundation of modular, high quality, open source components such as Parquet,
Arrow and DataFusion. and we should focus our efforts as a community on
improving these components rather than building new file formats that are
optimized for narrow use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come Join Us! 🎣 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/contributor-guide/communication.html"&gt;
&lt;img alt="https://datafusion.apache.org/" class="img-responsive" src="/blog/images/logo_original4x.png" width="20%"/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the Author&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andrewalamb/"&gt;Andrew Lamb&lt;/a&gt; is a Staff Engineer at
&lt;a href="https://www.influxdata.com/"&gt;InfluxData&lt;/a&gt;, and a member of the &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/"&gt;Apache
DataFusion&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://arrow.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Arrow&lt;/a&gt; PMCs. He has been working on
Databases and related systems more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About DataFusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/"&gt;Apache DataFusion&lt;/a&gt; is an extensible query engine toolkit, written
in Rust, that uses &lt;a href="https://arrow.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Arrow&lt;/a&gt; as its in-memory format. DataFusion and
similar technology are part of the next generation &amp;ldquo;Deconstructed Database&amp;rdquo;
architectures, where new systems are built on a foundation of fast, modular
components, rather than as a single tightly integrated system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://datafusion.apache.org/contributor-guide/communication.html"&gt;DataFusion community&lt;/a&gt; is always looking for new contributors to help
improve the project. If you are interested in learning more about how query
execution works, help document or improve the DataFusion codebase, or just try
it out, we would love for you to join us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;: This trend is described in more detail in the &lt;a href="https://www.influxdata.com/blog/flight-datafusion-arrow-parquet-fdap-architecture-influxdb/"&gt;FDAP Stack&lt;/a&gt; blog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;: This layout is referred to a &lt;a href="https://www.vldb.org/conf/2001/P169.pdf"&gt;PAX in the
database literature&lt;/a&gt; after the first research paper to describe the technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;: Benchmaxxing (verb): to add specific optimizations that only
impact benchmark results and are not widely applicable to real world use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt;: Hive Style Partitioning is a simple and widely used form of indexing based on directory paths, where the directory structure is used to
store information about the data in the files. For example, a directory structure like &lt;code&gt;year=2025/month=08/day=15/&lt;/code&gt; can be used to store data for a specific day
and the system can quickly rule out directories that do not match the query predicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;5&lt;/code&gt;: I am also convinced that we can speed up the process of parsing Parquet footer
with additional engineering effort (see &lt;a href="https://xiangpeng.systems/"&gt;Xiangpeng Hao&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="https://www.influxdata.com/blog/how-good-parquet-wide-tables/"&gt;previous blog on the
topic&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href="https://github.com/etseidl"&gt;Ed Seidl&lt;/a&gt; is beginning this effort. See the &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/arrow-rs/issues/5854"&gt;ticket&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;6&lt;/code&gt;: ClickBench includes a wide variety of query patterns
such as point lookups, filters of different selectivity, and aggregations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="footnote7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;code&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;: For example, &lt;a href="https://github.com/zhuqi-lucas"&gt;Zhu Qi&lt;/a&gt; was able to speed up reads by over 2x 
simply by rewriting the Parquet files with Offset Indexes and no compression (see &lt;a href="https://github.com/apache/datafusion/issues/16149#issuecomment-2918761743"&gt;issue #16149 comment&lt;/a&gt;) for details).
There is likely significant additional performance available by using Bloom Filters and resorting the data
to be clustered in a more optimal way for the queries.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>